Guide to the Salomon Chaim Bochner Papers, 1914-1982 MS 357
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
- Series II: Scholarly Works, 1923-1982
  Manuscripts of scholarly works make up a large and significant gathering of research material. Bochner wrote many versions of his many articles and books. These files reveal the evolution of his thought from handwritten notes to the completed manuscript. Most items are full of deleted paragraphs, insertions, and marginal comments. A great majority of his publications after his arrival in the United States in 1932 are represented here. Moreover, some of the works found here were never published: the handwritten notes to lectures, articles and books that were started but never finished, and a major book which Bochner was near completing upon his death. The title given each file follows as closely as possible Bochner's own label for the item or the name of the eventual publication to which it pertained. The entire series is arranged in alphabetical order by title. Among items of the same title, an attempt was made to arrange them according to the chronology of their creation, not publication, in order to reveal the sequence of revisions. When it was possible to ascertain an exact date, it was given in the inventory. A printout of all of the bibliographical citations to Bochner's publications in chronological order is in the control file of the collection and is available to researchers upon request.
  - Achievements of Bernhard Riemann, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Achievements of Riemann, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Advanced Analysis, c. 1935 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Ages of Mathematics, c. 1975 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Ages of Mathematics, c. 1975 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Albert Einstein: What He Was and What He Did, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 22-24)
  - Almost Automorphy, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Almost Periodic Functions, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Almost Periodicity for Abstract Differential Equations (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Almost Periodicity (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Analysis (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Analytic Measures on Compact BOHR Groups (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Approximation by Spherical Summability (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Aristotle's Notion of Place (Topos) in Physics (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Aristotle's Physics and Today's Physics (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Aristotle's Physics and Today's Physics (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Atoms, Continuity (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Atoms and Other Particles (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Birth of the Modern Scientific Instrument (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Boolean Algebra (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - But What Is Continuity? (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Commentary on the Paper of Curtis A. Wilson, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Continuity All Around (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Continuity and Discontinuity in Nature and Knowledge (Box 3, Folder 42-48)
  - Continuity vs. Atomism (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Continuous Mappings of Almost Automorphic and Almost Periodic Functions, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Curvature and Beti Numbers in Real and Complex Vector Bundles (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Differential Geometry (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Differential Geometry in Vector Bundles (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Duality Theorems (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Earth and Universe (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Eclosion and Synthesis, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 8-32)
  - Einstein and the Twentieth Century (Box 4, Folder 33-34)
  - Einstein Between Centuries, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 35-38)
  - Einstein Between Centuries, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
  - Electromagnetic Spectrum (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - The Emergence of Analysis (Prolegomena) (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - The Emergence of Analysis, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Everything Has A History (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Everything Is Continuous (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Fade-Out Into the Sunset (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Fourier Series Came First, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Function of Several Complex Variables, 1935 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Function Rings and Analytic Measures (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - General Almost Automorphy, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Greatness of the Nineteenth Century (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Greek Mathematics (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Green Stokes Formula (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Harmonic Analysis and Probability, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 18-21)
  - Harry Bateman, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Hermann Weyl, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - History of Mathematics as a Part of General History, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - History of Mathematics as a Part of General History, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Horizontalism (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - How Aristotle Created History of Natural Philosophy, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - How Aristotle Created History of Natural Philosophy, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - How History of Science Differs From Other History (Box 5, Folder 29-34)
  - Humanities (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Irrationality vs. Rationality (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Infinity, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Infinity in Nature and Knowledge (Box 5, Folder 38-39)
  - Infinity in Nature and Knowledge (Box 5, Folder 40-43)
  - Intellectual Role of Mathematics Since Renaissance and Scientific Revolution, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Intrinsic Analytic Continuation and Envelopes of Holomorphy (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Intrinsic Analytic Continuation and Envelopes of Holomorphy (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Kaehler Property (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Kepler, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Kepler, Einstein, Spengler: The Role of Space in Nature and Knowledge (Preface), 1980 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Kepler, Einstein, Spengler: The Role of Space in Nature and Knowledge (Chapter 1), 1980 (Box 5, Folder 49-53)
  - Kepler, Einstein, Spengler: The Role of Space in Nature and Knowledge (Chapter 1), 1980 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Kepler, Einstein, Spengler: Space in Nature, Knowledge, Art (Chapter II), 1980 (Box 6, Folder 2-4)
  - Kepler, Einstein, Spengler: Space in Nature, Knowledge, Art (Chapter III), 1980 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Knowledge in the Nineteenth Century (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Konrad Burdach: Reformation, Renaissance, Humanism (Preface) (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Levels of Mathematics in Interaction with Science, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 8-13)
  - Limitations of Greek Mathematics (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Linguistics (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Mathematical Background Space in Astronomy and Cosmology, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Mathematical Background Space in Astronomy and Cosmology, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Mathematical "Firsts' in the Nineteenth Century (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - A Mathematical Outlook on the Scientific Revolution, 1500-1800 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - A Mathematical Outlook on the Scientific Revolution, 1500-1800 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Mathematical Reflections, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Mathematical Reminiscences and Americana: The Philosophical Conception of Continuity in C. S. Peirce, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 22-23)
  - Mathematical Space in Nature and Knowledge, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 24-34)
  - Mathematics (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Mathematics and Renaissance in Italy, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 36-39)
  - Mathematics in Cultural History (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Mathematics: Its History as a Part of Cultural History, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Mechaniks (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Nineteenth Century: An Overview (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Notes on Abel's Theorem (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Notes on "Weimar Culture, Causality and Quantum Theory, 1918-1927." (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - Number Theory Notes (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Number Theory Notes (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - Our Theme (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Oswald Spengler, Mathematician, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - Oswald Spengler, Mathematician, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 1-4)
  - Oswald Spengler: Mathematician and Philosopher of Doom (Box 7, Folder 5-8)
  - Partial Ordering (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Partial Ordering (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Partial Ordering (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Partielle Differentialgleiden, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Partielle Differentialgleiden, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Pessimism (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Physics (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Plato on Mathematics (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Positivity of the Heat Kernel for Ultra Spherical Polynomials, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Positivity of the Heat Kernel for Ultra Spherical Polynomials, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Lectures on Potential Theory, 1934 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Lectures on Potential Theory, 1934 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Principles of Probability, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Program in History of Knowledge, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Psychology and Pedagogy (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Regular Polyhedra (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Research Proposal in Linear Differential-Difference Equations, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Review of Gustav Herglotz: Gesamnelte Schriften, by Hans Schwerdtfeger, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Review of Gustav Herglotz: Gesamnelte Schriften, by Hans Schwerdtfeger, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Review of The Rational Mechanics of Flexible or Elastic Bodies, 1638-1788 by C. Truesdell, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 28-30)
  - Revolutions in Physics and Crises in Mathematics (Box 7, Folder 31-32)
  - The Rise of Functions (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - The Role of Mathematics in the Development of Science (Box 7, Folder 34-42)
  - The Role of Mathematics in the Development of Science (Revision Inserts) (Box 7, Folder 43-45)
  - Several Complex Variables (Box 7, Folder 46-48)
  - The Significance of Some Basic Mathematical Conceptions for Physics (Box 7, Folder 49)
  - Singularities and Discontinuities, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 50-51)
  - Size of the Universe in Greek Thought (Box 7, Folder 52-53)
  - Space, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 54-55)
  - Space and Structure (Box 7, Folder 56)
  - Symmetry and Asymmetry, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 57)
  - Symmetry and Asymmetry, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Symmetry and Asymmetry, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Tabelion Theorems and the Prime Number Theorem (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Theory of Measure (Box 8, Folder 4-6)
  - Theory of the Distribution of Primes (Chapter I) (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Theory of the Distribution of Primes (Chapter I) (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Three Dimensionality in Antiquity (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Three Dimensionality and Anti-Substance (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Space and Universe in Western Thought (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Three Dimensionality (Box 8, Folder 12-17)
  - Throwbacks to Pythagorism (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Transportation, Communication, Illumination (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Twentieth Century: Arts (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Uniform Convergence of Monotone Sequence of Functions (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Vector Fields on Riemannian Spaces With Boundary (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Weak Solutions of Linear Partial Differential Equations (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - What Are Stars Made Of? (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Why Mathematics? (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Why Mathematics? (Box 8, Folder 26)
- Series III: Teaching Materials and Notebooks
  This category contains some of the teaching materials Bochner collected during his long career as a teacher at Munich, Princeton, and Rice, and the numerous notebooks he kept throughout his life. The two were grouped together because many of the notebooks contain teaching notes as well as language drills, poetry, a short diary, and more advanced mathematical notations.
  - Teaching Materials
    - Algebra (Notes), 1931 (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - Analytical Geometry (Notes), 1931 (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - Differential Geometry (Notes), 1931 (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - Algebra II (Notes), 1932 (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - Mathematics 107 (Examination), 1942 (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - Mathematics 107 (Handouts), 1970 (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - Mathematics 221 (Problems), 1972 (Box 8, Folder 33)
    - Mathematics 222 (Problems), 1972-1975 (Box 8, Folder 34)
    - Mathematics 221 (Examinations, Problems), 1972-1977 (Box 8, Folder 35)
    - Mathematics 221 (Examinations, Problems), 1972-1977 (Box 8, Folder 36)
    - Mathematics 221 (Notes), 1974 (Box 8, Folder 37)
    - Mathematics 211 (Examinations, Problems), 1975 (Box 8, Folder 38)
    - Mathematics 212 (Examinations, Problems), 1976 (Box 8, Folder 39)
    - Mathematics 212 (Notes), 1976 (Box 8, Folder 40)
    - Mathematics 402b (Notes), 1977 (Box 8, Folder 41)
    - Mathematics 402d (Problems), 1977 (Box 8, Folder 42)
    - Mathematics 401 (Problems), 1977-1978 (Box 8, Folder 43)
    - Mathematics 222 (Examination), 1978 (Box 8, Folder 44)
    - Mathematics 426 (Examination), 1979 (Box 8, Folder 45)
  - Notebooks
    - Mathematics Notebook, 1924 (Box 8, Folder 46)
    - Mathematics Notebook, 1919 (Box 8, Folder 47)
    - Mathematics Notebook, 1924 (Box 8, Folder 48)
    - Mathematics and Spanish Language Notebook (Box 8, Folder 49)
    - Transcript, University of Berlin, 1918-1921 (Box 8, Folder 50)
    - German Language Drills, c. 1917 (Box 8, Folder 51)
    - Mathematics Notebook, c. 1920 (Box 8, Folder 52)
    - German Language Drills, c. 1917 (Box 8, Folder 53)
    - Diary and Poetry, c. 1922 (Box 8, Folder 54)
    - Mathematics Notebook, 1920 (Box 8, Folder 55)
    - Mathematics Notebook, 1924 (Box 8, Folder 56)
    - Mathematics Notebook, 1924 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Mathematics and English Language Notebook, c. 1920 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Algebra Exercises of Josefa V. Schwarz, Munich, c. 1930 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Algebra Exercises of Josefa V. Schwarz, Munich, c. 1930 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Student Exercises in Mathematics, Munich, 1928 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Mathematics Notebook, 1926 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Reading Notes on Greek Mathematics, c. 1960 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Reading Notes on Ancient Greek Classics, c. 1960 (Box 9, Folder 8)
- Series IV: Personal Documentation, 1914-1981
  This series is comprised of legal and financial documents, personal references, and photographs. The legal and financial documents include wills, publishing and consultant contracts, diplomatic papers, personal bills, high school and university transcripts, military records, receipts, royalty statements, diplomas, certificates, insurance claims, and medical records. Arranged in chronological order from 1914 to 1981, they provide some early biographical data regarding Bochner's education in Poland and Germany, his citizenship, and his military service during World War I. They also give a glimpse of his financial dealings with publishers, particularly Princeton University Press.
  The personal references from teachers and employers were written in the form of general statements concerning Bochner's moral and academic characteristics rather than as true letters to specific individuals. For this reason, they were not included in the correspondence category. The four such statements in the collection, all within the period 1915-1924, are from his preparatory school in Berlin, the Konigstadtisch Oberrealschule, his professor at the University of Berlin, Issal Schur, the Cuten and Syman banking firm, where he worked for almost a year, and Josef Wdowinski, for whom Bochner worked as a secretary.
  The twenty-seven photographs of the collection consist of mostly unidentified snapshots of Bochner and his colleagues and family in Munich, Princeton, Houston, Los Angeles, and Bombay from c.1928 to c. 1981.
  - Legal and Financial Papers, 1914-1981. (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - References, 1915-1924 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Photographs, c. 1928-1981 (Box 9, Folder 11)
- Series V: Printed Material, 1925-1979
  The printed material within the collection is of two types: off-prints and books. The off-prints, collected by Bochner throughout his life and consisting of many articles that are now hard to obtain, were divided between those that were written by Bochner himself and those written by others. The former group was arranged in chronological order and the latter in alphabetical order. Although Bochner's library was large, only books written by him or those in which he made annotations were retained with the collection. They were arranged in alphabetical order by author.
  - Off-Prints
    - Publications of Salomon Bochner
      - 1925-1929 (Box 9, Folder 12)
      - 1930-1934 (Box 9, Folder 13)
      - 1935-1937 (Box 9, Folder 14)
      - 1938-1939 (Box 9, Folder 15)
      - 1940-1941 (Box 9, Folder 16)
      - 1942-1944 (Box 9, Folder 17)
      - 1945-1947 (Box 9, Folder 18)
      - 1948-1949 (Box 9, Folder 19)
      - 1950-1951 (Box 9, Folder 20)
      - 1952-1954 (Box 9, Folder 21)
      - 1955-1957 (Box 9, Folder 22)
      - 1958-1959 (Box 9, Folder 23)
      - 1960-1962 (Box 9, Folder 24)
      - 1963-1964 (Box 9, Folder 25)
      - 1965-1969 (Box 9, Folder 26)
      - 1970-1979 (Box 9, Folder 27)
      - Undated (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - Publications of Others
      - A (Box 9)
      - A-B (Box 10)
      - B-C (Box 11)
      - C-F (Box 12)
      - F-H (Box 13)
      - H-K (Box 14)
      - K-L (Box 15)
      - L-M (Box 16)
      - M-N (Box 17)
      - N-R (Box 18)
      - S-T (Box 19)
      - T-Z (Box 20)
- Series VI: Oversize
  - Oversize materials (Box 21, Folder 1)